F. Charles Adler Papers
F. Charles Adler Papers
1787-1959
1936-1955
Adler, F. Charles, (Frederick Charles), 1889-1959
9 linear ft.
Correspondence; printed material, including articles, clippings, programs; and phonodiscs. A large part of the correspondence pertains to the organization and development of the Saratoga Spa Music Festival, predecessor of the Saratoga Performing Arts Center seasonal concert series. Writings include those of Adler and his wife, Hannah Moriarta Adler. Memorabilia includes financial material and an assortment of printed items, including clippings, programs, publicity, research material, and reviews. Programs include those relating to Adler’s work with the Federal Music Project (1936-1941). Recordings consist mostly of Saratoga Spa Music Festival recordings.
144579
Biographical History
The F. Charles Adler Papers is a collection of materials, including correspondence, writings, and memorabilia, which reflects the conductor's career from 1936 through 1955. Born in London in 1889, Adler began his career in the United States as conductor of the New York Festival Orchestra, a component of the Federal Music Project which was sponsored by the Works Progress Administration. With his interest in contemporary musical compositions coupled with a belief that the most fertile ground for the growth of American music was outside the country's large cities, Adler founded the New York Chamber Orchestra in 1945, and shortly thereafter transferred his base of operations to Gansevoort, New York. Composed of selected members of the Philharmonic-Symphony Society of New York (later known as the New York Philharmonic), the New York Chamber Orchestra performed more than 40 new compositions at the Saratoga Spa Music Festival during the 1946-1947 seasons. Adler died in Vienna in 1959 at the age of 69.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Correspondence-Subject files (Boxes 1-13) contain both incoming and outgoing letters and related material, most of which was generated between 1936 and 1955, with composers, conductors, musicians and musicologists. Correspondence which is of greatest volume includes that with composers George Antheil, Will Gay Bottje, Charles Wakefield Cadman, Robert Casadesus, Avery Claflin, Henry Cowell, Norman Dello Joio, Arcady Dubensky, Vernon Duke, Isadore Freed, Anis Fuleihan, Vittorio Giannini, Eugene Goossens, Edward Burlingame Hill, Frederick Jacobi, Philip James, Werner Josten, Ernst Krenek, Otto Luening, Jacques de Menasce, Darius Milhaud, Douglas Moore, Paul Amadeus Pisk, Vittorio Rieti, Roger Sessions, Elie Siegmeister, Virgil Thomson, Ernst Toch, Burnet C. Tuthill, John W. Work, and Eric Zeisl; conductors Theodore Bloomfield, Dimitri Mitropolous, Alex North, and Leopold Stokowski; musicians Claire Coci, John Corigliano, Albert Elkus, Rudolf Kolisch, Boris Koutzen, Louis Krasner, Ray Lev, Eugene List, Carl Stern and John Wummer; and musicologists Oliver Daniel, Alfred Einstein, and H.C. Robbins Landon. The Correspondence-Subject files also contain a substantial amount of correspondence relating to the American Composers Alliance, the American-Soviet Music Society, the Bruckner Society of America Inc., the Philharmonic-Symphony Society of New York, the Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc., and the Society for the Publication of American Music, Inc. as well as that of a number of music publishers and recording studios, including Am-Rus Editions, Associated Music Publishers Inc., Boosey and Hawkes Inc., Elkan-Vogel Co., Carl Fischer, Inc., Edward B. Marks Music Corporation, Leeds Music Corporation, Music News, Inc., Sesac Inc., SPA Records (of which Adler was artistic director), Southern Music Publishing Company, Inc., Unicorn Records, and Vanguard Recording Society, Inc.
Memorabilia (Boxes 15-18) includes financial material and an assortment of printed items, including clippings, programs, publicity, research material, and reviews. The financial material is divided into Adler's personal expenses and bank transactions, and those relating to the Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc. Printed material includes various clippings and other items relating to Adler's sojourn in Austria in the early 1950s, his affiliation with the New York Chamber Orchestra, and miscellaneous personal notices. Programs include those relating to Adler's work with the Federal Music Project (1936-1941), concerts conducted by Adler in Germany, concerts for the Saratoga Spa Music Festival, and various miscellaneous concerts which Adler conducted as well as those with which he was not associated, but for which he received material. Publicity includes flyers and advance notices for miscellaneous concerts. Research material encompasses Adler's collection of clippings and articles pertaining to music, while reviews include those relating to Adler's career (1952-1953) as well as those of SPA Records. Memorabilia concludes with a selection of miscellaneous items, including articles, clippings, publicity and reviews which relate to the Saratoga Spa Music Festival.
Recordings (phonodiscs) include transcriptions (pressings made for distribution to radio stations) of the Saratoga Spa Music Festivals for 1937, 1946 and 1947 and an assortment of test pressings of SPA records. Although the ID numbers assigned to these items go up to adler_fc_089, there are in fact only 87 phonodiscs.
Writings (Box 14) include those of Adler, his wife Hannah Moriarta Adler, and a poem by an unidentified author, "Good Time Charlie On the Loose." Adler's writings include transcripts of an Open Forum discussion at Skidmore College between Adler and Frederick Schang, president of Columbia Artists Management, Inc., on the role of concert management in fostering an appreciation of music; program notes; miscellaneous manuscripts; and published material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Series are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each series, material is arranged alphabetically by topic or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; New York State; Adler, F. Charles (Frederick Charles), 1889-1959.; Adler, Hannah Moriarta.; Federal Music Project (U.S.); Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc.; United States -- Work Projects Administration.; United States -- Works Progress Administration.; Composers -- United States; Conductors (Music) -- United States; Music -- 20th century.; Music festivals -- New York (State); Musicians -- United States.; Saratoga Springs (N.Y.) -- History; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; 78 rpm records.; Programs (documents); Reviews (documents); Composers.; Conductors (Music); Musicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Hannah Moriarta Adler, 1972.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - A, 1 folder (Box 1)
  - Abbey, Denise (Box 1)
  - Adler, Clarence (Box 1)
  - Ahn, Eak Tai (Box 1)
  - Albany Institute of History and Art (Box 1)
  - American Automobile Association (Box 1)
  - American Composers Alliance, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Musicians (Box 1)
  - American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers (ASCAP) (Box 1)
  - American-Soviet Music Society (Box 1)
  - Am-Rus Editions (Box 1)
  - Anderson, Florence (Box 1)
    See also DuPage, Richard
  - Anthiel, George, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Aschner, Bernard (Box 1)
  - Associated Hospital Service of New York (Box 1)
  - Associated Music Publishers, Inc., 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Audio-Scriptions, Inc. (Box 2)
  - B, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Balogh, Erno (Box 2)
  - Barber, Samuel (Box 2)
  - Bardos, Arthur A., See Rot-Weiss-Rot
  - Barrington-Coupe, W.H. (Box 2)
  - Barzun, Jacques (Box 2)
  - Beer-Walbrunn, Maria (Box 2)
  - Behrendt, Lydia, See Hoffman-Behrendt, Lydia
  - Benjamin, Edward B. (Box 2)
  - Bilotti, Anton (Box 2)
  - Blaukopf, Kurt (Box 2)
  - Bloomfield, Theodore (Box 2)
  - Bonner, Eugene MacDonald (Box 2)
  - Boosey and Hawkes, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Bosmans, Arthur (Box 2)
  - [Ed.] Bote and G. Bock (Box 2)
  - Bottje, Will Gay (Box 2)
  - Brand, Max (Box 2)
  - Brendel, Alfred (Box 2)
  - Broadcast Music, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Bruckner Society of America (Box 2)
  - Burdick, Lawrence & Moncsko (Box 2)
  - Bureau International de l'Edition Mecanique (BIEM) (Box 2)
  - C, 1 folder (Box 2)
  - Cadman, Charles Wakefield, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Capitol Records (Box 2)
  - Carman, Harry J., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Carnegie Hall (Box 2)
  - Carpenter, John Alden (Box 3)
  - Carragan, Howard, See Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute
  - Casadesus, Robert (Box 3)
  - Casella, Alfredo (Box 3)
  - Cesana, Otto (Box 3)
  - Chasins, Abram (Box 3)
  - Chavez, Carlos (Box 3)
  - [J.W.] Chestet, Ltd. (Box 3)
  - Christlieb, Don (Box 3)
  - Circle Blue Print Company (Box 3)
  - Claflin, Avery (Box 3)
    See also American Composers Alliance
  - Clayburgh, Alma (Box 3)
  - Cluett & Sons (Box 3)
  - Coci, Claire (Box 3)
  - Cole, Lois Dwight, See Whittlesey House
  - Columbia Artists Management, Inc., See Columbia Concerts Inc.
  - Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc. (Box 3)
  - Columbia Concerts Inc., 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Columbia Transcriptions (Box 3)
  - Committee for Netherlands Music (Box 3)
  - Concert Management Arthur Judson, Inc., See Columbia Concerts Inc.
  - Concert Program Magazines, See Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc.
  - Constable, William George (Box 3)
  - Copland, Aaron (Box 3)
  - Corigliano, John (Box 3)
  - Cosden, Nell (Mrs. Joshua S,) (Box 3)
  - Cowell, Henry, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - D, 1 folder (Box 3)
  - Daniel, Oliver, See American Composers Alliance
  - De Angilis, Joseph (Box 3)
  - Dello Joio, Norman (Box 3)
  - Dembinsky, William (Box 3)
  - Dobyns, Cordelia, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Dowling, Walter, See United States Foreign Service
  - Downes, Olin (Box 3)
  - Downs, Thomas McKean (Box 3)
  - Drucker, Vladimir (Box 3)
  - Dubensky, Arcady (Box 3)
  - Duke, Vernon (Box 3)
  - DuPage, Richard (Box 3)
    See also Anderson, Florence
  - Eastman School of Music (Box 4)
  - Eddy, Spencer B., See Saratoga Spa and Music Festival, Inc.
  - Editions Salabert (Box 4)
  - Edson, Bernard (Box 4)
  - Effinger, Cecil (Box 4)
  - Einstein, Alfred (Box 4)
  - Elkan-Vogel Co., 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Elkus, Albert (Box 4)
  - Elmore, Cyrus B., See Saratoga Spa and Music Festival, Inc.
  - Encyclopedia Britannica (Box 4)
  - Endich, Sara Mae (Box 4)
  - Epstein, Lonny (Box 4)
  - Erskine, John (Box 4)
  - Etler, Alvin (Box 4)
  - Eureka Specialty Printing Co. (Box 4)
  - F, 1 folder (Box 4)
  - Fairchild, Henry Pratt (Box 4)
  - Farmer, Virginia (Box 4)
  - Federal Music Project, See Memorabilia: Printed Material: Programs
  - Feist, Leonard, See Mercury Music Corporation
  - [Carl] Fischer, Inc. (Box 4)
  - [Edwin H.] Fleischer Music Collection (Free Library of Pennsylvania) (Box 4)
  - Fox, Harry (Box 4)
  - Fox, Norman A., See SPA Records
  - Francis, Muriel (Box 4)
  - Fraser, Morris & Co., Inc. (Box 4)
  - Freed, Isadore (Box 4)
  - Freedman, Elaine (Box 4)
  - Friedphil Realty Corp. (Box 4)
  - Fuleihan, Anis (Box 4)
  - G, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Ganz, Rudolph (Box 5)
  - Gaskins, Ben A., See Columbia Concerts Inc.
  - General Electric Company (Box 5)
  - Giannini, Vittorio, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Girden, William M. (Box 5)
  - Glasounow, Alexander (Box 5)
  - Gold Star Recording Studios (Box 5)
  - Goldberg & Wolff, See Hays, Wolff, Schwabacher, Sklar and Epstein
  - Goossens, Eugene (Box 5)
  - Goss, Robert (Box 5)
  - Graf, Uta (Box 5)
  - Graham, Robert (Box 5)
  - Granetman, Lola (Box 5)
  - [H.W.] Gray Company (Box 5)
  - Greene, Winthrop S. (Box 5)
  - Greissle, Felix, See Edward B. Marks Music Corporation
  - Grey, Robert G., See Bruckner Society of America
  - Guarnieri, Camargo (Box 5)
  - Guenther, Felix (Box 5)
  - Gutman, John (Box 5)
  - H, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - Haefner, Maria (Box 5)
  - Harris, Roy (Box 5)
  - The Hartford Times (Box 5)
  - Hays, Wolff, Schwabacher, Sklar & Epstein, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Hayward, Dolores (Box 5)
  - Hendl, Walter (Box 5)
  - Hill, Edward Burlingame, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Hindemith, Paul (Box 5)
  - Hoffman-Behrendt, Lydia (Box 5)
  - Huberman, Bronislaw (Box 5)
  - Hubert, Dave L., See New Sound
  - I, 1 folder (Box 5)
  - J, 1 folder (Box 6)
  - Jacobi, Frederick, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Jacobi, Irene (Box 6)
  - Jadeson, Walter J. and Annemarie, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Jaffe, Herman (Box 6)
  - James, C. Lindell, See Unicorn Records
  - James, Philip, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Johns, Louis Edgar (Box 6)
  - Johnson, Wright and Anne (Box 6)
  - Josten, Werner, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Judson, Arthur, See Columbia Concerts Inc.
  - Juilliard School of Music (Box 6)
  - K, 1 folder (Box 7)
  - [Walter] Kaner Associates, 2 folders (Box   7)
  - Karlin, Henry (Box 7)
  - Katz, David (Box 7)
  - Kaye, Harold (Box 7)
  - Keller, Harold, See New York (State). Department of Commerce
  - Kenny, Margarita (Box 7)
  - Keresey, Howard W. (Box 7)
  - Kerr, Harrison (Box 7)
  - Kolisch, Rudolf (Box 7)
  - Korngold, Erich Wolfgang (Box 7)
  - Kotschnig, Walter, See United States. Department of State
  - Koussevitsky, Serge (Box 7)
  - Koutzen, Boris (Box 7)
  - Krasner, Louis (Box 7)
  - Kmety, Violet, See Zenith Radio Corporation
  - Krenek, Ernst, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Krueger, Karl (Box 7)
  - Kurtz, Efrem (Box 7)
  - Kurzweil, Fredric (Box 7)
  - L, 1 folder (Box 7)
  - Landon, H.C. Robbins (Box 7)
  - Last, Siegmund (Box 7)
  - Lawner, Max (Box 7)
  - Leavitt. Max (Box 7)
  - Leeds Music Corporation (Box 7)
  - Lees, Benjamin (Box 7)
  - Legler, ? (Box 7)
  - Lehman, Herbert H. (Box 7)
  - Leighton & Nelson, Advertising (Box 7)
  - Lenchner, Paula (Box 7)
  - Lev, Ray (Box 7)
  - List, Eugene (Box 7)
  - Little, Paul (Box 7)
  - Loewenstein, Karl (Box 7)
  - Lopatnikoff, Nikolai (Box 7)
  - Luening, Otto (Box 7)
  - M, 1 folder (Box 7)
  - McDonald, Harl (Box 7)
  - Macdonald, Robert M.S., See Rot-Weiss-Rot
  - McKinney, Laurence, See Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc.
  - Macmillan, Ernst (Box 7)
  - Mahler, Alma (Box 7)
  - Makower, Mary (Box 8)
  - [Alfred J.] Mapleson (Box 8)
  - [Edward B.] Marks Music Corporation, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Martin Music Management (Box 8)
  - Marvin, Frederick (Box 8)
  - Matfeld, Julius, See Columbia Broadcasting System, Inc.
  - Mathews, Elizabeth, See Columbia Concerts Inc.
  - Meik, Siegfried (Box 8)
  - Menasce, Jacques de (Box 8)
  - Mercury Music Corporation (Box 8)
  - Metropolitan Musical Bureau, Inc., See Columbia Concerts Inc.
  - Milhaud, Darius (Box 8)
  - Mitchell, Donald (Box 8)
  - Mitropolous, Dimitri (Box 8)
  - Moore, Douglas (Box 8)
  - Moore, Henry T. (Box 8)
  - Mundy, John (Box 8)
  - Music News, Inc., 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Musical Courier (Box 8)
  - Musicraft Corporation (Box 8)
  - N, 1 folder (Box 8)
  - Nagy, Elmer (Box 8)
  - National Concert and Artists Corporation (Box 8)
  - National Concert Magazines, See Saratoga Spa Music Festival Inc.
  - National Music League, Inc. (Box 8)
  - National Poster Stamp Society (Box 8)
  - Neuman, Herman, See WNYC (radio station)
  - New England Music Critics Symposium, 1948; See The Hartford Times
  - New Sound (Box 8)
  - New York (State) Department of Commerce (Box 8)
  - New York Public Library (Box 8)
  - Newlin, Dika (Box 9)
  - Nola Recording Studios (Box 9)
  - Nola n & Twichell Advertising Agency, Inc. (Box 9)
  - North, Alex (Box 9)
  - Novik, Morris S. (Box 9)
    See also WNYC (radio station)
  - Noyes, Pierrepont B., See Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc.
  - Nozzi, Michel (Box 9)
  - Oesterreichische Lehrmittelanstalt (Box 9)
  - O'Neil, Perry (Box 9)
  - Orkin, Ruth (Box 9)
  - Ornest, Naomi, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Outhwaite, Gilbert B. (Box 9)
  - Ovanin, Nikola Leonard (Box 9)
  - Owen, Bessie (Box 9)
  - P, 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Pan American Union, Music Division (Box 9)
  - Parke-Bernet Galleries, Inc. (Box 9)
  - Pauly, Rose (Box 9)
  - Peck, C.L. (Box 9)
  - Persichetti, Vincent (Box 9)
  - [C.F.] Peters Corporation (Box 9)
  - Philharmonic-Symphony Society of New York, See Van Praag, Maurice
  - Philosophical Library (Box 9)
  - Piket, Frederick (Box 9)
  - Pisk, Paul Amadeus, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Pogany, Imre (Box 9)
  - Price, Vincent (Box 9)
  - Quasha, William H. (Box 9)
  - R, 1 folder (Box 9)
  - Radhuber, Guenther (Box 9)
  - Rathaus, Karol (Box 9)
  - Ratner, Leonard G. (Box 9)
  - Ravag (Box 9)
  - Read, Gardner (Box 9)
  - Record Hunter (Box 9)
  - Reichle, Elisabeth (Box 9)
  - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (Box 9)
  - Renzi, Dorothy (Box 9)
  - Rieti, Vittorio (Box 9)
  - Roche, Emmeline (Box 9)
  - Rodzinski, Artur (Box 9)
  - Rosenberger, Walter E. (Box 9)
  - Rosenker, Michael (Box 10)
  - Rosenthal, Leon and Fanny J. (Box 10)
  - Rosenwald, Hans, See Music News, Inc.
  - Rot-Weiss-Rot (Box 10)
    See also United States Foreign Service
  - Rothe, Friede F., See Tourel, Jennie
  - Roy, Klaus George (Box 10)
  - Rozsa, Miklos (Box 10)
  - Rubin, David W. (Box 10)
  - S, 1 folder (Box 10)
  - Saratoga Musical Union (Box 10)
  - Saratog Spa Music Festival, Inc., 1937-1951; 15 folders (Box 10)
    See also Carman, Harry J., New York (State) Department of Commerce, Van Praag, Maurice
  - Saratoga Springs Authority, See Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc.
  - Sargent, Malcolm (Box 11)
  - Saxton, Stanley, See Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc.
  - [G.] Schirmer, Inc. (Box 11)
  - Schnabel, Artur (Box 11)
  - Schnabel, Helen (Box 11)
  - Schnabel, Karl Ulrich (Box 11)
  - Schnabel, Therese (Box 11)
  - [Artur] Schnabel Memorial Committee (Box 11)
  - Schollum, Robert (Box 11)
  - [B.] Schott's Sohne (Box 11)
  - Schuller, Arthur (Box 11)
  - Schuster, Joseph (Box 11)
  - Schwartz, Paul (Box 11)
  - Scott, Tom, See American Composers Alliance
  - Secunda, Sholom (Box 11)
  - Seeger, Charles, See Pan American Union, Music Division
  - Segal, Elizabeth (Box 11)
  - Sesac Inc., 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Sessions, Roger (Box 11)
  - Shilkret, Arthur (Box 11)
  - Shilkret, Nathaniel (Box 11)
  - Shuman, Davis (Box 11)
  - Siegmeister, Elie (Box 11)
  - Siena, Frank E.R., See Saratoga Spa Music Festival Inc.
  - Simmons, Mary (Box 11)
  - Skornia, Harry J., See Rot-Weiss-Rot
  - Slade, John and Caroline (Box 11)
  - Sloss, M.C. (Mrs.) (Box 11)
  - Society for the Publication of American Music, Inc., See James, Philip
  - Society of Participating Artists, Inc., See SPA Records
  - Solomon, Carlton Z. (Box 11)
  - Solomon, Maynard and Seymour, See Vanguard Recording Society, Inc.
  - Sorrell, Lise (Box 11)
  - Southern Music Publishing Company, Inc. (Box 11)
  - Sowerby, Leo (Box 11)
  - SPA Records (Box 11)
  - Spain Travel Agency (Box 11)
  - Spaulding, E. Wilder, See United States Foreign Service
  - Stern, Carl (Box 11)
  - Stichting Donemus (Box 11)
  - [B.F.] Stevens & Brown Ltd. (Box 11)
  - Still, William Grant (Box 11)
  - Stillman-Kelley, Jessie (Box 11)
  - Stokowski, Leopold (Box 11)
  - Stueckgold, Grete (Box 11)
  - Sullivan, Frank (Box 11)
  - Sutermeister, Heinrich (Box 12)
  - Szell, George (Box 12)
  - T, 1 folder (Box 12)
  - Talbot, Ona B. (Box 12)
  - Tatham Stamp & Coin Company (Box 12)
  - Taylor, Deems, See American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers
  - [Alec] Templeton (Box 12)
  - Terry, Milton, See United States Foreign Service
  - Thompson, Llewellyn E., See United States Foreign Service
  - Thomson, Virgil (Box 12)
  - Tidmarsh, Elmer A., 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Toch, Ernest (Box 12)
  - Tourel, Jennie (Box 12)
  - Trimble, David (Box 12)
  - Tuthill, Burnet C. (Box 12)
  - U, 1 folder (Box 12)
  - Unicorn Records (Box 12)
  - United States Department of State (Box 12)
  - United States Foreign Service (Box 12)
    See also Rot-Weiss-Rot
  - United States Work Projects Administration, See Memorabilia: Printed Material: Programs - Federal Music Project (WPA)
  - United States Work Progress Adminstration, See Memorabilia: Printed Material: Programs - Federal Music Project (WPA)
  - Universal Edition A.G. (Box 12)
  - Van Gordon, Cyrena (Box 12)
  - Vanguard Recording Society, Inc. (Box 12)
  - Van Praag, Maurice, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Vassar College (Box 12)
  - Vernon, Ashley (Box 12)
  - Vieland, Joseph (Box 12)
  - Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra (Box 12)
  - W, 1 folder (Box 12)
  - WGY (radio station) (Box 12)
  - WNYC (radio station) (Box 12)
  - WQXR (radio station) (Box 12)
  - Wagner, Joseph Frederick (Box 12)
  - Walleck, Oskar (Box 12)
  - Walter, Bruno (Box 12)
  - Waters, Patti (Box 13)
  - Webster, Frances (Box 13)
  - Weintraub, Eugene (Box 13)
  - Werfel, Alma Mahler, See Mahler, Alma
  - Werner, Vivian L. (Box 13)
  - White, Walter (Box 13)
  - Whithorne, Emerson (Box 13)
  - Whittlesey House (Box 13)
  - Wildgans, Friedrich (Box 13)
  - Williams, Alexander (Box 13)
  - Woolley, Monty, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Work, John W. (Box 13)
  - Wummer, John and Mildred (Box 13)
  - Y, 1 folder (Box 13)
  - Young Men's Christian Association of Tahawus (Box 13)
  - Yugoslav Information Center (Box 13)
  - Zeisl, Eric (Box 13)
  - Zenith Radio Corporation (Box 13)
  - Zimbalist, Efrem (Box 13)
  - Unidentified (Box 13)
- Memorabilia
  - Financial
    - Personal, 10 folders (Box 15)
    - Saratoga Spa Music Festival, Inc., 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Legal - Hannah Moriarta Adler (Box 16)
  - Printed material
    - Personal
      - Austria, 3 folders (Box 16)
      - New York Chamber Orchestra, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Programs
      - Federal Music Project (WPA), 1936-1941; undated; 5 folders (Box 16)
      - Germany (photostats) (Box 17)
      - Saratoga Spa Music Festival Inc. (Box 17)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
    - Publicity
      - Miscellaneous concerts (Box 17)
    - Research material, 11 folders (Box 17)
    - Reviews
      - Personal, 1952-1953 (Box 17)
      - SPA Records (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 17, 18)
  - Printer's block - Adler image (conducting at Saratoga Spa Music Festival) (Box 18)
  - Saratoga Spa Music Festival, 8 folders (Box 18)
- Recordings, audio, Although the assigned ID numbers go up to adler_fc_089, there are in fact only 87 phonodiscs.
  - [Black Howard Home Recording Disc], adler_fc_089; 1 78RPM phonodisc; no content information available at this time
  - [Galway - Darla Dancer], adler_fc_029; 1 78RPM phonodisc; titles in pencil on disc
  - [unidentified phonodisc] I/1 & 2, Kohn Bela Phono-Studio, adler_fc_082; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - [unidentified phonodisc] II/1 & 2, Kohn Bela Phono-Studio, adler_fc_081; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - [unidentified phonodisc] III/1 & 2, Kohn Bela Phono-Studio, adler_fc_083; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - [unidentified phonodisc] Melo Tone Recording Studio, adler_fc_080; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - Adagio From String Quintet By Anton Bruckner - Side 2, 03/21/1945; adler_fc_016; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - Adagio From String Quintet By Anton Bruckner - Sides 1 and 3, 03/21/1945; adler_fc_015; 1 78 RPM phonodisc
  - Alma Mater, adler_fc_084; 1 78 RPM phonodisc
  - Ballades #1, 2 & 4 - Brahms - Anne Marie Spaeth, July 1952; adler_fc_087; 1 78 RPM phonodisc
  - Bruckner 9th - Side 4, adler_fc_034; Columbia test pressing; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - Charles Adler Cond. Concert Orchestra - Side 3, 06/19/1941; adler_fc_09; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - Charles Adler Cond. Concert Orchestra - Sides 1 and 4, 06/19/1941; adler_fc_010; 1 78RPM phonodisc
  - Charles Adler Cond. Concert Orchestra - Sides 2 and 5, 09/18/1937; adler_fc_004; Labeled as "Haydn’s Symphony "; 1 78 RPM phonodisc
  - Charles Adler Cond. WNYC Symphony Orchestra - Sides 1 and 4, 10/26/1941; adler_fc_023; 1 78 RPM phonodisc
  - Charles Adler Cond. WNYC Symphony Orchestra - Sides 2 and 5, 10/26/1941; adler_fc_021; 1 78 RPM phonodisc